Guide to the Papers of Mark Popovskii,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Mark Popovskii Papers,
1980-1986
Popovskiĭ, Mark Aleksandrovich, 1922-.
21 linear feet (48 document boxes).
Columbia University, Bakhmeteff Archive, Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, N.Y. 10027.
4078435
Biographical Note
Russian author who emigrated to the United States in 1977. Editor of journal "Strana i mir," and author of numerous books on scientific subjects including "The Vavilov Affair," "Manipulated Science," and "The Story of Dr. Haffkine.
Scope and Content
Papers of Mark Popovskii, including corrected and annotated photocopied typescripts of his books "Russkie muzhiki rasskazyvaiut" (the story of Tolstoy's peasant followers in the U.S.S.R. during the period 1918 to 1977) and "On, ona i sovetskaia vlast'" (English title: "Sex in the Soviet Union"). Also included are questionnaires and interviews with Soviet emigres regarding their opinions of contemporary sex customs in the Soviet Union.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 15 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Questionnaires
Series III: Arranged Correspondence
Series IV: Writings
Series V: Research Materials
Series VI: Readers' Response
Series VII: About Popovskii
Series VIII: Diaries
Series IX: Writings by Others
Series X: Printed Materials
Series XI: Photographs
Series XII: Video
Series XIII: Books ny Popovskii
Series XIV: Scrapbooks
Series XV: Audio
Subjects
Tolstoy, Leo, graf, 1828-1910--Appreciation--Soviet Union.; Peasantry--Soviet Union.; Sex customs--Soviet Union.; Interviews
Access Restrictions
Names of interviewees are not to be cited or quoted.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
01/--/87 B-87-2-10 Papers Popovskii, Mark Gift
Gift of Mark Popovskiĭ, 1987.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  Series contains Popovskii's original correspondence with prominent Russian literary figures
  - Aksenov, Vasilii to: Popovskii, Mark, VT, Jun. 20, 1984, (1p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    [Letter, accompanied the essay on Akhmadulina, Bella (essay not found)]
  - Aleshkovskii, IUz to: Popovskii, Mark, n.p., [May 23, 1984], (1 a.c.s.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dovlatov, Sergei to: Popovskii, Mark, Forest Hills, NY, Jun. 7, 1988, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Popovskii, Mark to: Dovlatov, Sergei, New York, NY, Jun. 11, 1988, (1p. t.l.s. (photocopy)) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Elagin, Ivan to: Popovskii, Mark, n.p., [1985] - 1986, (1p. t.l.s., 1p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    [re: Writers in Exileresearch]
  - Popovskii, Mark to: Genis, Aleksandr, [New York, NY], Dec. 11, 1994, (1p. a.l.s. (photocopy)) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Genis, Aleksandr to: Popovskii, Mark, Edgewater, NJ, Dec. 1996 - Dec. 1998, (4 a.c.s.) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gorenshtein, Fridrikh to: Popovskii, Mark, West Berlin, Dec. 1985 - Aug. 1986, (3 a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Popovskii, Mark to: Grekova, I (Venttsel', Elena Sergeevna), New York, NY, May 2, 1989, (3p. t.l.s. (photocopy), 1p. a.n. by Popovskii - news clipping) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Grekova, I (Venttsel', Elena Sergeevna) to: Popovskii, Mark, Moscow, USSR, May 25, 1989, (1p. a.l.s., 2p. news clipping) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Guberman, Igor' to: Popovskii, Mark, Jerusalem, Israel, Apr. 20, 1988, (1 a.c.s.) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Guberman, Igor' to: Kitaevich, IUlii, USSR, Oct. 1985 - Aug. 1987, (2 a.l.s. (photocopy)) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - IAnovskii, V. S. (Vasilii S.) to: Popovskii, Mark, Rego Park, NY, Sep. 1984 - Apr. 1989, (1p. a.l.s., 1p. a.n.s., 1p. t.d.s. (photocopy)) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ianovskaia, Izabella to: Popovskii, Mark, Rego Park, NY, Apr. - Aug. 1989, (1p. a.l.s., 1p. a.n.s., 1p. t.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    [Wife of IAnovskii, V.S.]
  - Korotych, Vitalii to: Popovskii, Mark, New York, NY; Boston, MA, Aug.- Oct. 1991, (1p. a.l.s., 1p. t.l.s) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Korzhavin, N. (Mandel, Naum) to: Popovskii, Mark, Boston, MA, Nov. 11, 1985, (1 a.c.s.) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Men', Aleksandr to: Popovskii, Mark, Novaia Derevnia (Moscow Region), USSR, Mar. 1989 - Aug. 1990, (4 a.c.s., 2 a.l.s., 2p. transcripts - letters of Jan 28, Feb 27, Jun. 3, 1990) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Razgon, Lev to: Popovskii, Mark, Moscow, Russia, Jun. 1992 - Aug. 1998, (3 t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Popovskii, Mark to: Razgon, Lev, New York, NY, Dec. 1991 - [1998], (1p. a.l.s., 1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Roziner, Feliks to: Popovskii, Mark, Tel-Aviv, Israel; Boston, MA, May 1984 - Feb. 1987, (5 a.l.s., 1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sapgir, Kira to: Popovskii, Mark, Paris, France, Sep. 1987, (35p t.l.s., 1p. t.l.s., 6 typed poems) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Popovskii, Mark to: Sapgir, Kira, New York, NY, Sep. 14, 1987, (1p. t.l.s. (photocopy)) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Voinovich, Vladimir to: Popovskii, Mark, n.p., Oct. 15, 1985, (1p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Popovskii, Mark to: Voino-IAsenetskii, Valentin Feliksovich (Luka), Moscow, USSR, Sep. 24, 1957, (2p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Voino-IAsenetskii, Valentin Feliksovich (Luka) Archbishop of Crimea and Simferopol to: Popovskii, Mark, [Crimea, USSR], Oct. 11, 1957, (1p. l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Voino-IAsenetskii, Valentin Feliksovich (Luka) Archbishop of Crimea and Simferopol to: [...], Piotr Petrovich, [Crimea, USSR], 1959, (1p. t.l., 1p. t.d.) (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series II: Questionnaires
  Part of research project Writers in Exile, these questionnaires were sent to Russian émigré writers residing in North America. Responses vary from brief fill-in answers to multi-page free-form letters. Many responces have marks by Popovskii on the margins.
  - Agafonov, Vasilii (Gantman, IUlian), n.p., Dec. 19, 1992, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Antonovich, Aleksandr, New York, NY, Jan. 28, 1993, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Aksenov, Vasilii, Washington, DC, Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Armalinskii, Mikhail, Minneapolis, MN, Dec. 19, 1992, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Arzunian, Edvig, n.p., n.d., (5p. a.d.) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Belavina, Nonna, Long Island, NY, Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d., 1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Berdan, IUrii, Elmhurst, NY, Jan. 17, 1993, (2p. a.d., 2p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bliznetsova, Ina, Irvington, NY, [Feb. 1993], (2p. a.d., 1p. a.n., 1p. t.l.) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Bobyshev, Dimitrii, Champaigne, IL, Jan. 17, 1993, (6p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Bogachinskaia, Inna, New York, NY, [Nov. 12], 1993, (1p. t.d., 1p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Brodsky, Joseph, Rome, Italy, Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 28)
    [Draft of letter by Popovskii enclosed]
  - Burova, Nina F. n.p., n.d., (2p. a.d., 1p. a.l. ) (Box 1, Folder 29)
    [Letter written on the back side of the questionnaire (2nd page)]
  - Dimer, Evgeniia, West Orange, NJ, Dec. 29, 1992, (1p. t.d., 1p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Dizhur, Bella, n.p., Jan. 13, 1993, (1p. t.d.c., 1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Draitser, Emil, n.p., Jan. 8, 1993, (2p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Druskin, Aleksandr, Brooklyn, NY, Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d.) (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Druzhnikov, IUrii, n.p., Dec. 31, 1992, (5p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Efimov, Igor' Markovich, n.p., Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d.) (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Ezerskaia, Bella, n.p., Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d.) (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Fessenko, Tatiana, n.p., Feb. 13, 1993, (1p. l.) (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Genis, Aleksandr, n.p., n.d., (2p. a.d. (photocopy)) (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Gershgorin, Bela, Far Rockaway, NY, [Jan. 1993], (2p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Gershgorin, Roman, n.p., Jan. 28, 1993, (3p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Gert, IUrii, Cleveland, OH, Dec. 23, 1992, (2p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Girshin, Mark, Richfield Springs, NY, Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Hollerbach, Serge, n.p., Dec. 31, 1992, (2p. a.d., 1p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Ivanov, Sergei, n.p., Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d. (photocopy), 1p. t.d.) (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Kafanova, Liudmila, New York, NY, Jan. 1993, (2p. a.d.) (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Kapelian, Grigorii, Jersey City, NJ, [Jan. 1993], (2p. a.d.) (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Kashkarov, IUrii, n.p., Jan. 12, 1993, (1p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Khalif, Lev, Far Rockaway, NY, Dec. 1992, (2p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Kliueva, Elena, Brooklyn, NY, n.d., (2p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Kogan, Mark, n.p., n.d., (2p. a.d.) (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Kotlikov, Rudol'f, Chicago, IL, n.d., (2p. t.l.) (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Kovalev, Konstanin, Brooklyn, NY, Jan. 3, 1993, (8p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 52)
    [CHANGE E NA E: (yo)]
  - Kozlovskii, Vladimir, n.p., n.d., (1p. t.d., 1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Krasnoshchekova, Elena Aleksandrovna, GA, Jan. 11, 1993, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Kreid, Vadim, Iowa City, IA, Dec. 31, 1992, (2p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Ktorova, Alla (Sandor, Victoria), Rockville, MD, Dec. 21, 1992, (1p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Kuz'minskii, Konstantin K. n.p., Jan. 31, 1993, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Lanina, Aleksandra, Canada, n.d., (2p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Lemkhin, Mikhail, n.p., Dec. 24, 1992, (2p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Lempert, Simon (Kontorovich, Simon), West Hartford, CT, Dec. 24, 1992, (2p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Liubin, Evgenii, East Hanover, NJ, Dec. 1992, (1p. t.d.) (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Losev, Lev, Hanover, NH, Dec. 21, 1992, (1p. t.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Matlin, Vladimir, n.p., Dec. 24, 1992, (2p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Miuge, Sergei, Jersey City, NJ, Feb. 19, 1993, (1p. a.l.s., 1p. clipping) (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Murav'ev, P. (Petr Aleksandrovich), n.p., Jan. 1993, (2p. a.d.) (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Naumov, Aleksandr (Naimark, Il'ia), n.p., n.d., (2p. t.d.) (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Navrosov, lev, Riverdale, NY, n.d., (5p. a.d.) (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Paramonov, Boris, n.p., n.d., (2p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Perel'man, Viktor, Leonia, NJ, Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d.) (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Petrov, V. P. (Viktor Porfirievich), n.p., Jan. 31, 1993, (2p. a.d., 1p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Podgorbunskii, Mark, Bronx, NY, Feb. 1, 1993, (2p. a.d.s., 2p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Polchaninov, R. V. (Rostislav), New Hyde Park, NY, Dec. 23, 1992, (1p. a.d.s., 1p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Popovskii, Mark, New York, NY, n.d., (2p. a.d.) (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Rachko, Marina (Efimova), n.p., Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d.) (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Raigorodskii, R. n.p., n.d., (1p. a.d) (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Rappoport, Vitaly; Miliutina, Katia Letter by Miliutina, Cresskill, NJ, [Dec. 26], 1992, (1p. a.l.s., 1p. a.d. (photocopy))
  - Reznik, Semen, n.p., Dec. 29, 1992, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Riazanovsky, Alexander V. n.p., Jan. 23, 1993, (2p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Rudiak, Il'ia, Northbrook, IL, Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Ryskin, Grigorii, n.p., Dec. 29, 1992, (1p. a.d, 1p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Sagalovskii, Naum, n.p., n.d., (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Shraer-Petrov, David, n.p., Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Shrayer, Maxim, New Haven, CT, Jan. 3, 1993, (2p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Shtern, Liudmila, n.p., Feb. 11, 1993, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Shvarts, Anatolii, n.p., Dec. 28, 1992, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Sil'ver, Raisa, n.p., Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Sinkevich, Valentina, Philadelpia, PA, Dec. 23, 1992, (2p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Sirotin, Aleksandr, Brooklyn, NY, Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d.) (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Skorov, Valerii (Skoropistsev), n.p., Jan. 1993, (1p. t.l.) (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Soifer, Valerii, n.p., Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Soloviev, Vladimir, n.p., Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Suslov, Il'ia Petrovich, Derwood, MD, Dec. 30, 1993, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Svirskii, Grigorii, n.p., Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Temkina, Marina, New York, NY, n.d., (2p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Troll', IUlia, n.p., n.d., (3p. t.d.) (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Turovskii, Anatolii, n.p., Dec. 22, 1992, (1p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Vainer, Mikhail, Rockville, MD, Dec. 27, 1992, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Venclova, Tomas, n.p., Dec. 29, 1992, (2p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Vetrov, Boris (Levant, Benedikt), n.p., Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d., 1p. t.d.) (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Volin, Mikhail (Ponomarev, Mikhail), Denver, CO, Dec. 23, 1992, (1p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Volkov, Solomon, New York, NY, Feb. 18, 1993, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Young, Cathy, n.p., n.d., (2p. a.d.) (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Zubareva, Vera, Philadelpia, PA, Dec. 1992, (1p. a.d.s.) (Box 1, Folder 102)
- Series III: Arranged Correspondence
  Series contain Popovskii's business and personal correspondence, predominantly from his New York period (1978 - 2000). Enclosed photographs were separated into Photographsseries. Paper enclosures (news clippings, postcards, literary works) kept on file. 1980 - 1987 letters from friends and family in USSR are addressed to Efim Rabinovich - evidently a nickname for Popovskii in order to confuse the Soviet censure.
  - Subseries III.1: Prominent Individual Correspondents
    Individual files of prominent correspondents ( friends and colleages of Mark Popovskii) arranged alphabetically by last name. Included into this subseries are individuals featured in Popovskii's writings, or individuals with large (over 10 items) body of correspondence. Also included is photocopy correspondence with notable Russian writers. Files contain incoming and copies of outgoing correspondence, arranged chronologically.
    - Armalinskii, Mikhail ( Peltsman, Mikhail) M.I.P. Company, Minneapolis, MN, 1985 - 1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Bezdetskaia, Tat'iana, IAlta, Crimea, 1997 - 1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Bokarius, Marina; Bokarius, Aleksei, St.-Petersburg, Russia, 1994 - 2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Chalidze, Valerii Four letters from Popovsky (copies) on publishing the manuscript by Ivan Filimonov (real name: Obolonskii, Aleksandr) in the publication SSSR-Vnutrennie Protivorechiia, edited by Chalidze, New York, NY, 1987 - 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Chichibabin, Boris Letter from Popovsky (copy), New York, NY, Mar. 1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Ciobanu, Vasile Translator of Zhisn' and Zhitieinto Romanian, Kishinev, Moldova; 1994 - 1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Danivov, Nicholas American Journalist in USSR. Moscow, Russia, 1983 - 1987 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      [John Hall - nickname of Popovskii in correspondence with Danilov]
    - Dizhur, Bella, Brooklyn, NY, 1987 - 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Druzhnikov, IUrii University of California, Davis, Moscow, USSR; Vienna, Austria; Davis, CA, 1985 - 1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Farber, IAkov Chief doctor of the Hospital named after Archbishop Luka Voino-IAsenetskii, prominent citizen of Tambov, Tambov, Russia, 1994 - 1998 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Hammer, Darrell P.; Hammer, Louise B. Indiana University, Department of Political Science Louise Hammer continued the correspondence after the death of Darrell Hammer in 1998. 1984 -1988 correspondence deals with sociologist Aleksandr Obolonskii (referred to as nash drug- our friend) and publishing of his work (referred to as rukopis'- the manuscript)., Moscow, USSR; Helsinki, Finland; Bloomington, IN, 1984 - 1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      [See also Chalidze, Valerii and Obolonskii, Aleksandr (in Arrandged Corresondence - O).]
    - Kazarnovskaia, Mina Primarily incoming letters from a personal friend. Moscow, USSR, 1984 - 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      [See also Pervova, IUlia (frequently mentioned in Mina's letters). Their early letters were often interleaved.]
    - Khazanov, Boris (Faibusovich, Gennadii) 1985-1990 correspondence deals primarily with Strana I Mirmagazine, edited by Khazanov and Liubarskii, with Popovskii as the American representative., Munich, Germany, 1985 - 2000 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      [See also Liubarskii, Kronid and Strana I Mir correspondence folders.]
    - Kraineva, Elena, Moscow, Russia, 1994 - 2000 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      [School friend]
    - Levitin-Krasnov, A. E. (Anatolii Emmanuilovich), Lucerne, Switzerland, 1984 - 1989 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      [Popovskii's secretary in early 1970s]
    - Liubarskii, K. A. (Kronid Arkad'evich) Correspondence re: Strana I Mirmagazine, edited by Khazanov and Liubarskii, with Popovskii as the American representative., Munich, Germany, 1985 - 1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      [See also Khasanov, Boris and Strana I Mir correspondence folders.]
    - Maksimova, Olga, Montreal, Canada, 1985 -1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Pervova, IUlia Primarily incoming letters from a personal friend. Kiev, Ukraine, 1984 - 2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      [See also Kazarnovskaia, Mina (frequently mentioned in Pervova's letters). Their letters were frequently interleaved.]
    - Pinsky, Oleg Correspondence with the Russian emigrant - US prison inmate, High Desert State Prison, Susanville, CA; Pelican Bay State Prison, Crescent City, CA, 1998 - 2000 (Box 3, Folder 4 - 6)
    - Sarnov, Benedict Letter from Popovsky (copy), New York, NY, Jan. 1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Sorokina, Marina Russian Academy of Science Archive Rossiiskaia Akademiia Nauk - Arkhiv, on acquisition of Popovskii's diaries, Moscow, Russia, 1997 - 2000 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Svirskii, Grigorii, Toronto, Canada, 1986 - 1999 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Svirskii, Vladimir, Tivon, Israel; Migdal-Ha-Emek, Israel, 1996 - 2000 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Vladimov, Georgii Confidential letter from Popovsky (copy), with evaluation of contemporary russian émigré writers, New York, NY, Sep. 1983 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Voino-IAsenetskaia, Ol'ga Valentinovna; Voino-IAsenetskaia, Tat'iana Correspondence with the family of Voino-IAsenetskii, Valentin Feliksovich (Archbishop Luka), character of Popovskii's book Zhizn' and Zhitie of Voino-Iasenetskii, Odessa, Ukraine; Ialta, Ukraine; Chicago, IL; San Francisco, CA, [1990s] (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Vol'fson, Vladimir (Zeev), Rishon Le Ziyon,Israel, 1983 - 1989 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Zelickman, Engelina, Jerusalem, Israel, 1988 - 1998 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Subseries III.2: Publishers
    Popovskii's business correspondence with periodicals and publishers. Arranged alphabetically by corporate name.
    - Proffer, Carl; Proffer Ellendea; Meyer, Ronald Ardis, Ann Arbor, MI, 1983 - 1989 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Alloi, Vladimir Atheneum, Paris, France, 1987 - 1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Malenkovich, Vladimir Forum Copy of outgoing letter, Munich, Germany, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Pirozhkova, Vera Golos Zarubezh'ia, Munich, Germany, 1984 - 1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Samsonova-Breitbart, Ekaterina; Zhilkina, Tat'iana Grani Copies of outgoing letters, Frankfurt am Main, Germany; Moscow, Russia, 1987 - 1999 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Efimov, Igor' Hermitage Includes business and personal correspondence with Efimov, Tenafly, NJ, 1984 - 2000 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Sedykh, Andrei (TSvibak, IAkov); Shakhova, Liudmila; Vainberg, Valerii (Weinberg, Lawrence) Novoye Russkoye Slovo, New York, NY, 1979 - 1997 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Maloradovich, Serafim; Karsov, Nina Overseas Publications Interchange, Ltd. (OPI), London, UK, 1979 - 1990 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Polovets, Aleksandr Panorama, Los Angeles, CA, 1986 - 2000 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Zhdanov, Nikolai Possev Publishing House, Frankfurt am Main, Germany, 1985 - 1989 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Finkel'shtein, Eitan; Antonovich, A; Conan, Clara, Hazanov, Boris; Liubarskii, Kronid; Gertner, Mikhail; [...], Mara. Strana I Mir Business correspondence between Popovskii as the magazine's American representative with the Munich staff. For letters addressed individually to Liubarskii and Khazanov see their folders in Arranded Correspondence- Individuals, Munich, Germany, 1986 - 1990 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Perel'man, Victor Vremia I My, Leonia, NJ, 1986 - 1988 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Shmeman, Natalia; Struve, Nikita YMCA-Press, Paris, France, 1978 - 1993 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Posnova, Irina Zhizn' S Bogom, Brussels, Belgium, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - 24 Chasa; Forverts; Novyi Zhurnal; Poberezh'e; Russkaia Mysl'; Vechernii New York; Vestnik; Russian-Language Newspapers. Outgoing letters to editors., USA, 1991 - 1999 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Anan'ev, Anatolii; Brianskaia, I; Enisherlov, V. P.; Gushchin, L. N; Korotych, Vitalii; Luk'ianin, V.P.; Loshkareva, N. K,; Chuprinin, S. I; Ar'ev, A. IU; Zelenko, G. Literaturnaia Gazeta; Nashe Nasledie; Nauka I Religiia; Ogonek; Oktiabr'; Ural; Znamia; Znanie - Sila, Zvesda Russian periodicals after Perestroika. For Ogoneksee also Cataloged Correspondence - Korotych, Vitalii, Russia, 1990 - 1995 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Crossroad Publishing Co.; Doubleday & Co.; McMillan; Readers' Digest; Shoestring Press; Unwin Hyman, INc.Westview Press; William Morrow & Co.; US Publishing Houses, USA, 1979 - 1988 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Stasica, Ernest Ksiazka I Wiedza, Poland, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Subseries III.3: Family Correspondence
    - Vasilevskaia, Tatiana Vasil'evna, Moscow, Russia, 1984 - 1992 (Box 5, Folder 1 - 3)
      [Popovskii's former wife and authorized representative in Russia until her death in 1992. After Tatiana's death, Leonid Gurevich becomes Popovskii's authorized representative]
    - Popovskaia, Lilia, New York, NY, 1986 - 1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      [Wife]
    - Popovskii, Konstantin; Popovskaia Yevgeniia, Popovskii Platon; Popovskii Ignatii, St. Petersburg, Russia, 1987 - 2000 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      [Son Konstantin and his family]
    - Bishko, Genia, Leningrad, USSR;Jerusalem, Israel, 1987 - 2000 (Box 5, Folder 6 - 7)
      [Cousin ]
    - Khotmakher, Leiba, Odessa, Ukraine; Holstein, Germany, 1990 - 1998 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      [Stepfather]
    - Shadskaia, Inna; [...], Dina; [...], Teusch, Mikhail [and Lialia]; Kon, Alina; Popovskii, Aleksandr Other family members, 1985 - 1998 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Subseries III.4: Correspondence by subject
    - International Association of Soviet Political Prisoners -; Kongress Russkih Americantsev; Russian-American Associations, 1981, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Church community, 1984 - 1989 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Orthodox Church officials - letters regarding book about Voino-IAsenetskii, 1988 - 1999 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - US Politics, 1987 - 1989 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Outgoing correspondence re: Vavilov, Nikolai, 1987 - 1989 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Subseries III.5: Miscellaneous
    Arranged alphabetically by author, then chronologically. Approx. date span: 1969 - 2000
    - Abelev, Garry; Abrashkin, Petr; Aksel'rod, Elena; Al'tshuller, Boris (re: Miller, Larisa); Anikiev, Kirill; Archimovich, Kira; Arronet, Nikolai; Artem'eva, A.; Azmanov, Iskren; Correspondence: A (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Bagley, Peter; Bagration, Teimuraz; Balandina, Svetlana; Bandman, A.; Baranowski, Peter; Barmetova, Irina; Barnett, Don; Basov, Vasilii; Batchan, Aleksandr; Beilin, Boris; Belinkova (Iablokova), Natasha; Belogorskii, Anatolii; Ben-Iakov, Avram; Benigsen, Georgii; Berdichevskii, IEfim; Berkovich, Moisei; Billington, James H.; Biriukova, Ol'ga; Bisenko, [...]; Blestkina, Tat'iana; Blok, Viktor; Correspondence: Ba - Bn (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Bochstein, Boris; Boldyrev, Peter; Bondarenko, Alla; Borisov, Aleksandr; Bourikova, Svetlana; Brif, Mikhail; Braude, Benjamin; Brodsky, Hellen; Bulanov, Leonid; Bulashenko, Elena; Byrnes, Robert F.; Correspondence: Bo - Bz (Box 6, Folder 8)